Beau Lotto: So, this game is very simple.
بو لوتو: حسنا، هذه اللعبة في غاية البساطة.
All you have to do is read what you see. Right?
كل ما عليك القيام به هو قراءة ما تراه. أليس كذلك؟
So, I'm going to count to you, so we don't all do it together.
حسنا، سأقوم بالعد، حتى لا نفعل ذلك جميعا معا.
Okay, one, two, three.Audience: Can you read this?
حسنا، واحد، اثنين، ثلاثة. الجمهور: هل يمكنك قراءة هذا؟
BL: Amazing. What about this one? One, two, three.Audience: You are not reading this.
ب. ل: مذهل. وماذا عن هذه؟ واحد اثنان ثلاثة. الجمهور: أنتم لا تقرؤون هذا.
BL: All right. One, two, three. (Laughter)
ب. ل: حسنا. واحد اثنان ثلاثة. (ضحك)
If you were Portuguese, right? How about this one? One, two, three.
لو كنت برتغاليا، صحيح؟ ماذا عن هذه؟ واحد اثنان ثلاثة.
Audience: What are you reading?
الجمهور: ماذا تقرؤون؟
BL: What are you reading? There are no words there.
ب. ل: ماذا تقرؤون؟ ليست هناك كلمات.
I said, read what you're seeing. Right?
لقد قلت: اقرؤوا ما ترونه. أليس كذلك؟
It literally says, "Wat ar ou rea in?" (Laughter) Right?
إنه يقول حرفيا، "وات آر أو ري ين؟" (ضحك) أليس كذلك؟
That's what you should have said. Right? Why is this?
وهذا ما ينبغي أن يقال. أليس كذلك؟ لماذا هذا؟
It's because perception is grounded in our experience.
لأن الإدراك يقوم على أساس تجربتنا.
Right? The brain takes meaningless information
أليس كذلك؟ يأخذ الدماغ معلومات لا معنى لها
and makes meaning out of it, which means we never see
وينشئ منها معنى، مما يعني أننا لا نرى أبدا
what's there, we never see information,
ما يوجد هناك، ولا نرى أبدا المعلومات،
we only ever see what was useful to see in the past.
نحن نرى فقط ما كان مفيداً أن نراه في الماضي.
All right? Which means, when it comes to perception,
حسنًا؟ ما يعني أنه عندما يتعلق الأمر بالإدراك،
we're all like this frog.
نحن جميعا مثل هذا الضفدع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right? It's getting information. It's generating behavior
أليس كذلك؟ هو يحصل على معلومات. فيولّد سلوكا
that's useful. (Laughter)
مفيدا. (ضحك)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Video) Man: Ow! Ow! (Laughter) (Applause)
(الفيديو) الرجل: آه! آه! (تصفيق)
BL: And sometimes, when things don't go our way,
ب. ل: وفي بعض الأحيان، عندما لا تسير الأمور على طريقنا،
we get a little bit annoyed, right?
ننزعج قليلاً، أليس كذلك؟
But we're talking about perception here, right?
ولكن نحن هنا نتحدث عن الإدراك، صحيح؟
And perception underpins everything we think, we know,
والإدراك يمثل كل شيء نعتقده ونعلمه،
we believe, our hopes, our dreams, the clothes we wear,
ونؤمن به وآمالنا وأحلامنا والملابس التي نرتدي،
falling in love, everything begins with perception.
والوقوع في الحب، كل شيء يبدأ بالإدراك.
Now if perception is grounded in our history, it means
الآن إذا كان الإدراك يستند على تاريخنا، فإنه يعني
we're only ever responding according to what we've done before.
أننا فقط نستجيب بما يوافق ما قمنا به من قبل.
But actually, it's a tremendous problem,
ولكن في الواقع، فتلك مشكلة هائلة،
because how can we ever see differently?
لأنه كيف يمكننا على الإطلاق أن نرى بشكل مختلف؟
Now, I want to tell you a story about seeing differently,
الآن، أريد أن أحكي لكم قصة عن الرؤية بشكل مختلف،
and all new perceptions begin in the same way.
وجميع الإدراكات الجديدة التي تبدأ بنفس الطريقة.
They begin with a question.
إنها تبدأ بسؤال.
The problem with questions is they create uncertainty.
والمشكلة مع الأسئلة أنها تخلق حالة شك.
Now, uncertainty is a very bad thing. It's evolutionarily
الآن، الشك شيء سيء للغاية. إنه من الناحية التطورية
a bad thing. If you're not sure that's a predator, it's too late.
هو أمر سيئ. إذا كنت غير متأكد أن ذلك مفترس، سيكون الأمر متأخرا جدا.
Okay? (Laughter)
صحيح؟ (ضحك)
Even seasickness is a consequence of uncertainty.
حتى دوار البحر هو نتيجة ارتياب.
Right? If you go down below on a boat, your inner ears
أليس كذلك؟ إن ذهبت إلى الأسفل على متن قارب، آذانك الداخلية
are you telling you you're moving. Your eyes, because
تخبرك أنك تتحرك. وعيناك، ولأنها
it's moving in register with the boat, say I'm standing still.
تتحرك مع القارب، تقول أنك تقف ساكنا.
Your brain cannot deal with the uncertainty of that information, and it gets ill.
دماغك لا يمكنه التعامل مع ريبة تلك المعلومات، فيمرض.
The question "why?" is one of the most dangerous things you can do,
السؤال "لماذا؟" هو واحد من أخطر الأشياء التي يمكنك القيام بها،
because it takes you into uncertainty.
نظراً لأنه يأخذك إلى الشك.
And yet, the irony is, the only way we can ever
وحتى الآن، المفارقة هي أن السبيل الوحيد الذي يمكننا أبدا
do anything new is to step into that space.
أن نفعل أي شيء جديد هو أن نخطو في هذا الفضاء.
So how can we ever do anything new? Well fortunately,
فكيف يمكن لنا من أي وقت مضى القيام شيء جديد؟ حسنا من حسن الحظ،
evolution has given us an answer, right?
التطور قد أعطانا جوابا، صحيح؟
And it enables us to address even the most difficult
وقد مكننا من معالجة حتى أصعب
of questions. The best questions are the ones that create the most uncertainty.
الأسئلة. أفضل الأسئلة هي تلك التي تخلق أكبر ريبة.
They're the ones that question the things we think to be true already. Right?
إنها تلك التي تشكك في الأمور التي نعتقد أنها صحيحة بالفعل. أليس كذلك؟
It's easy to ask questions about how did life begin,
فمن السهل أن نسأل أسئلة حول كيف بدأت الحياة،
or what extends beyond the universe, but to question what you think to be true already
أو ما يمتد إلى ما بعد الكون، ولكن أن تسأل ما تعتقد أنه صحيح بالفعل
is really stepping into that space.
هو حقاً أن تدخل إلى ذلك الفضاء.
So what is evolution's answer to the problem of uncertainty?
فما هو جواب التطور لمشكلة الشك؟
It's play.
إنه اللعب.
Now play is not simply a process. Experts in play will tell you
الآن اللعب ليس مجرد عملية. خبراء اللعب سيخبرونكم
that actually it's a way of being.
أنه في الواقع طريقة حياة.
Play is one of the only human endeavors where uncertainty
اللعب هو أحد المساعي البشرية حيث يكون الشك
is actually celebrated. Uncertainty is what makes play fun.
في الواقع محتفى به. الشك هو ما يجعل اللعب ممتعا.
Right? It's adaptable to change. Right? It opens possibility,
أليس كذلك؟ إنه متكيف مع التغيير. صحيح؟ إنه يفتح إمكانية،
and it's cooperative. It's actually how we do our social bonding,
وهو تعاوني. هو في الواقع سبيلنا للترابط الاجتماعي،
and it's intrinsically motivated. What that means
وأنها مدفوعة جوهريا. ما يعنيه ذلك
is that we play to play. Play is its own reward.
هو أننا نلعب لنعب. اللعب هو مكافأة ذاته.
Now if you look at these five ways of being,
الآن إذا نظرتم إلى هذه الطرق الخمسة للحياة،
these are the exact same ways of being you need
هذه هي بالضبط نفس الطرق التي تحتاجها
in order to be a good scientist.
لتكون عالما جيدا.
Science is not defined by the method section of a paper.
العلم لا يتم تعريفه بقسم المنهج في بحث علمي.
It's actually a way of being, which is here, and this is true
إنه في الواقع أسلوب حياة، موجود هنا، وهذا صحيح
for anything that is creative.
بالنسبة لكل شيء إبداعي.
So if you add rules to play, you have a game.
فإذا أضفت قواعد للعب، تكون لديك لعبة.
That's actually what an experiment is.
وتلك في الواقع ماهية التجربة.
So armed with these two ideas,
لذا، مسلحا بهاتين الفكرتين،
that science is a way of being and experiments are play,
أن العلم أسلوب حياة، وأن التجارب هي ألعاب،
we asked, can anyone become a scientist?
تساءلنا، هل بإمكان أي كان أن يصبح عالما؟
And who better to ask than 25 eight- to 10-year-old children?
ومن أفضل لنسأله من 25 طفلا بعمر 8 إلى 10 سنوات؟
Because they're experts in play. So I took my bee arena
لأنهم خبراء في اللعب. لذا أخذت خلية نحلي
down to a small school in Devon, and the aim of this
إلى مدرسة صغيرة في ديفون، والهدف من ذلك
was to not just get the kids to see science differently,
كان هو ليس فقط جعل الأطفال ينظرون إلى العلوم بطريقة مختلفة،
but, through the process of science, to see themselves differently. Right?
ولكن رؤية أنفسهم بطريقة مختلفة من خلال منهج العلم. صحيح؟
The first step was to ask a question.
وكانت الخطوة الأولى هي طرح سؤال.
Now, I should say that we didn't get funding for this study
الآن، أود أن أقول أننا لم نحصل على تمويل لهذه الدراسة
because the scientists said small children couldn't make
لأن العلماء قالوا أن الأطفال الصغار لا يمكنهم تقديم
a useful contribution to science, and the teachers said kids couldn't do it.
مساهمة مفيدة للعلم، والمعلمون قالوا أن الأطفال لا يمكنهم القيام بذلك.
So we did it anyway. Right? Of course.
فقمنا بذلك على أي حال. أليس كذلك؟ طبعًا.
So, here are some of the questions. I put them in small print
لذا، إليك بعض الأسئلة. وضعتها بكتابة صغيرة
so you wouldn't bother reading it. Point is that five of the questions that the kids came up with
حتى لا تتعبوا أنفسكم بقراءتها. المقصد هو أن 5 من الأسئلة التي وضعها الأطفال
were actually the basis of science publication the last five to 15 years. Right?
كانت في الواقع أساس المنشورات العلمية في ال5 إلى 15 سنة الماضية. صحيح؟
So they were asking questions that were significant
وبالتالي فقد كانوا يطرحون أسئلة هامة
to expert scientists.
للعلماء الخبراء.
Now here, I want to share the stage with someone quite special. Right?
الآن هنا، أريد أن أشارك الخشبة مع شخص مميز جداً. أليس كذلك؟
She was one of the young people who was involved in this study,
لقد كانت واحدة من اليافعين الذين شاركوا في هذه الدراسة،
and she's now one of the youngest published scientists
وهي الآن واحدة من أصغر العلماء الذين نشر لهم
in the world. Right? She will now, once she comes onto stage,
في العالم. صحيح؟ سوف تكون الآن، بمجرد وصولها إلى الخشبة،
will be the youngest person to ever speak at TED. Right?
أصغر شخص على الإطلاق يتحدث في TED. صحيح؟
Now, science and asking questions is about courage.
الآن، العلم وطرح الأسئلة يتعلق بالشجاعة.
Now she is the personification of courage, because she's
الآن هي تجسيد للشجاعة، لأنها ستقوم
going to stand up here and talk to you all.
بالوقوف هنا، والتحدث معكم جميعا.
So Amy, would you please come up? (Applause)
حسنا إيمي، رجاء تفضلي. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So Amy's going to help me tell the story of what we call
ستقوم إيمي بمساعدتي في رواية القصة ما نسميه
the Blackawton Bees Project, and first she's going to tell you
مشروع نحل بلاكاوتون، وستقوم أولا بإخباركم
the question that they came up with. So go ahead, Amy.
بالسؤال الذي فكروا فيه، تفضلي إيمي.
Amy O'Toole: Thank you, Beau. We thought
إيمي أوتول: شكرا لك بو. كنا نظن
that it was easy to see the link between humans and apes
أنه من السهل أن نرى الصلة بين البشر والقرود
in the way that we think, because we look alike.
في الطريقة التي نفكر بها، نظراً لأننا نبدو سواسية.
But we wondered if there's a possible link
ولكننا تساءلنا إن كان هناك احتمال وجود صلة
with other animals. It'd be amazing if humans and bees
مع غيرها من الحيوانات. سيكون من المدهش إذا كان البشر والنحل
thought similar, since they seem so different from us.
يفكرون بشكل مماثل، حيث أنه يبدو مختلفا جدا عنا.
So we asked if humans and bees might solve
لذلك فكرنا فيما إذا كان البشر والنحل قد يحلون
complex problems in the same way.
المشاكل المعقدة بنفس الطريقة.
Really, we wanted to know if bees can also adapt
حقاً، أردنا أن نعرف إذا كان يمكن للنحل أيضا تكييف
themselves to new situations using previously learned rules
أنفسهم إلى حالات جديدة باستخدام قواعد وظروف مستخلصة
and conditions. So what if bees can think like us?
سابقا. ماذا لو أمكن للنحل التفكير مثلنا؟
Well, it'd be amazing, since we're talking about an insect
حسنا، سيكون ذلك مدهشا، إذ أننا نتحدث عن حشرة
with only one million brain cells.
تتوفر على مليون خلية دماغية فقط.
But it actually makes a lot of sense they should,
بل أنه في الواقع سيكون منطقيا جدا أن تستطيع،
because bees, like us, can recognize a good flower
لأن النحل، مثلنا، يمكنه التعرف على الزهرة الجيدة
regardless of the time of day, the light, the weather,
بغض النظر عن الوقت من اليوم، والضوء، والطقس،
or from any angle they approach it from. (Applause)
أو من أي زاوية يقترب منها. (تصفيق)
BL: So the next step was to design an experiment,
ب. ل: لذا الخطوة التالية كانت تصميم تجربة،
which is a game. So the kids went off and they designed
وهي لعبة. فقام الأطفال بتصميم
this experiment, and so -- well, game -- and so,
هذه التجربة، وهكذا -- حسنا، هي لعبة -- وهكذا،
Amy, can you tell us what the game was,
إيمي، هل بإمكانك إخبارنا ماذا كانت اللعبة،
and the puzzle that you set the bees?
واللغز الذي وضعتم للنحل؟
AO: The puzzle we came up with was an if-then rule.
إ. أ: اللغز الذي جئنا به كان قاعدة "إذا كان - فإن"
We asked the bees to learn not just to go to a certain color,
طلبنا من النحل تعلم ليس فقط الذهاب إلى لون معين،
but to a certain color flower only
ولكن إلى زهرة بلون معين فقط
when it's in a certain pattern.
عندما تكون في نمط معين.
They were only rewarded if they went to the yellow flowers
كانت تتم مكافأتهم فقط إن ذهبوا إلى الزهور الصفراء
if the yellow flowers were surrounded by the blue,
إذا كانت الزهور الصفراء محاطة باللون الأزرق،
or if the blue flowers were surrounded by the yellow.
أو إذا كانت الزهور الزرقاء محاطة بالصفراء.
Now there's a number of different rules the bees can learn
توجد هناك العديد من القواعد المختلفة التي يمكن للنحل تعلمها
to solve this puzzle. The interesting question is, which?
لحل هذا اللغز. السؤال المثير للإهتمام كان، أيها؟
What was really exciting about this project was we,
ما كان مثيرا حقاً في هذا المشروع هو أننا،
and Beau, had no idea whether it would work.
وبو، لم تكن لديه أي فكرة عما إذا كان هذا سيعمل.
It was completely new, and no one had done it before,
كانت جديدة تماما، ولا أحد قد فعل ذلك من قبل،
including adults. (Laughter)
بما في ذلك الكبار. (ضحك)
BL: Including the teachers, and that was really hard for the teachers.
ب. ل: بما في ذلك المعلمين، وذلك كان صعبا حقاً على المعلمين.
It's easy for a scientist to go in and not have a clue what he's doing,
من السهل على عالم أن يستمر وليست لديه أدنى فكرة عما يفعله،
because that's what we do in the lab, but for a teacher
لأن هذا ما نقوم به في المختبر، ولكن بالنسبة لمعلم
not to know what's going to happen at the end of the day --
عدم معرفة ما سيحدث في نهاية اليوم --
so much of the credit goes to Dave Strudwick, who was
يعود الكثير من الفضل إلى ديف سترودويك، والذي كان
the collaborator on this project. Okay?
المتعاون في هذا المشروع. حسنا؟
So I'm not going to go through the whole details of the study
لذا أنا لن أتطرق إلى التفاصيل الكاملة للدراسة
because actually you can read about it, but the next step
لأنه في الواقع يمكنك أن تقرأ عن ذلك، ولكن الخطوة التالية
is observation. So here are some of the students
هي المراقبة. هنا بعض من التلاميذ
doing the observations. They're recording the data
يقومون بالملاحظات. ويقومون بتسجيل بيانات
of where the bees fly.
أين يطير النحل.
(Video) Dave Strudwick: So what we're going to do —Student: 5C.
(فيديو) ديف سترودويك: إذن ما الذي سنقوم به – التلميذ: 5 سي.
Dave Strudwick: Is she still going up here?Student: Yeah.
ديف سترودويك: هل لا تزال ذاهبة إلى أعلى هنا؟ التلميذ: نعم.
Dave Strudwick: So you keep track of each.Student: Henry, can you help me here?
ديف سترودويك: حسنا فلتتعقب كلا منها. التلميذ: هنري، هل يمكنك مساعدتي هنا؟
BL: "Can you help me, Henry?" What good scientist says that, right?
ب. ل: "هل يمكنك مساعدتي، هنري؟" أي عالم جيد يقول ذلك، صحيح؟
Student: There's two up there.
التلميذ: هناك اثنان هناك.
And three in here.
وثلاثة هنا.
BL: Right? So we've got our observations. We've got our data.
ب. ل: صحيح؟ إذن فلدينا ملاحظاتنا. لقد حصلنا على بياناتنا.
They do the simple mathematics, averaging, etc., etc.
يجرون رياضيات بسيطة، بحساب المتوسط، إلخ، إلخ.
And now we want to share. That's the next step.
والآن نريد أن نشارك. تلك الخطوة التالية.
So we're going to write this up and try to submit this
لذا سنقوم بكتابة هذا، ونحاول إرساله
for publication. Right? So we have to write it up.
للنشر. صحيح؟ لذا علينا كتابته.
So we go, of course, to the pub. All right? (Laughter)
وهكذا فعلنا، بالطبع، نذهب إلى الحانة. صحيح؟ (ضحك)
The one on the left is mine, okay? (Laughter)
الكأس على اليسار هو ملكي، حسنا؟ (ضحك)
Now, I tell them, a paper has four different sections:
الآن، أخبرتهم، أن البحث العلمي فيه أربعة أقسام مختلفة:
an introduction, a methods, a results, a discussion.
مقدمة وعرض للأساليب والنتائج والمنقاشة.
The introduction says, what's the question and why?
المقدمة تتحدث عن السؤال ولماذا؟
Methods, what did you do? Results, what was the observation?
وعرض الأساليب عما قمنا به؟ النتائج، ماذا كانت الملاحظة؟
And the discussion is, who cares? Right?
والمناقشة، من يهتم؟ صحيح؟
That's a science paper, basically. (Laughter)
ذلك هو البحث العلمي، أساسا. (ضحك)
So the kids give me the words, right? I put it into a narrative,
إذن فالأطفال أعطوني الكلمات، صحيح؟ ووضعتها في سياق سردي،
which means that this paper is written in kidspeak.
مما يعني أن هذه الورقة مكتوبة بلغة أطفال.
It's not written by me. It's written by Amy
لست كاتبها. إنها مكتوبة من طرف إيمي
and the other students in the class. As a consequence,
وغيرها من الطلاب في الفصل. نتيجة لذلك،
this science paper begins, "Once upon a time ... " (Laughter)
تبدأ هذه الورقة العلمية هكذا، "كان يا ما كان ... "(ضحك)
The results section, it says: "Training phase, the puzzle ... duh duh duuuuuhhh." Right? (Laughter)
قسم النتائج يقول: "مرحلة التدريب، اللغز.. داه داه دااااهه." صحيح؟ (ضحك)
And the methods, it says, "Then we put the bees
وعرض الأساليب، يقول، "ثم نضع النحل
into the fridge (and made bee pie)," smiley face. Right? (Laughter)
في الثلاجة (ونصنع فطيرة نحل)، " وجه ضاحك. صحيح؟ (ضحك)
This is a science paper. We're going to try to get it published.
هذه ورقة علمية. سنحاول نشرها.
So here's the title page. We have a number of authors there.
حسنا هذه صفحة العنوان. لدينا عدد من المؤلفين هناك.
All the ones in bold are eight to 10 years old.
كل تلك التي بالخط العريض هي لمن هم في عمر 8 إلى 10 سنوات.
The first author is Blackawton Primary School, because
الكاتب الأول هو "المدارس الابتدائية لبلاكاوتون"، لأنه
if it were ever referenced, it would be "Blackawton et al,"
إذا تمت الإشارة إليها قط، فستكون "بلاكاوتون وآخرون"
and not one individual. So we submit it to a public access journal,
وليس فردا واحدا. فقمنا بإرسالها إلى دورية عمومية
and it says this. It said many things, but it said this.
وقد قالوا ما يلي. قالوا أشياء كثيرة، لكنه قال هذا.
"I'm afraid the paper fails our initial quality control checks in several different ways." (Laughter)
"أخشى أن الورقة العلمية لم تصل إلى معايير الجودة الأولية لدينا بعدة طرق مختلفة". (ضحك)
In other words, it starts off "once upon a time,"
وبعبارة أخرى، فإنها تبدأ بعبارة "كان يا ما كان،"
the figures are in crayon, etc. (Laughter)
والرسومات كانت بأقلام التلوين، إلخ (ضحك)
So we said, we'll get it reviewed. So I sent it to Dale Purves,
فقلنا، سنقوم بمراجعتها. فاتجهنا إلى ديل بورفس،
who is at the National Academy of Science, one of the leading neuroscientists in the world,
المتواجد في "الأكاديمية الوطنية للعلوم"، أحد علماء الأعصاب الرائدين في العالم،
and he says, "This is the most original science paper I have ever read" — (Laughter) —
فقال: "هذه الورقة العلوم الأكثر أصلية التي قرأتها على الإطلاق" -(ضحك)-
"and it certainly deserves wide exposure."
"هي بالتأكيد تستحق انتشارا أوسع".
Larry Maloney, expert in vision, says, "The paper is magnificent.
لاري مالوني، الخبير في الرؤية، يقول، "الورقة رائعة.
The work would be publishable if done by adults."
والعمل سيكون قابلا للنشر إن قام به الكبار."
So what did we do? We send it back to the editor.
لذا ما الذي فعلناه؟ أرسلناها مرة أخرى إلى المحرر.
They say no.
قالوا لا.
So we asked Larry and Natalie Hempel to write
فطلبنا من لاري وناتالي همبل أن يكتبا
a commentary situating the findings for scientists, right,
تعليقا يوضع النتائج للعلماء، صحيح،
putting in the references, and we submit it to Biology Letters.
بوضع المراجع، وقدمناه لـ"رسائل علم الأحياء".
And there, it was reviewed by five independent referees,
وهناك، تمت مراجعتها من طرف خمس حكام مستقلين،
and it was published. Okay? (Applause)
وتم نشره. حسنا؟ (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It took four months to do the science,
استغرقنا أربعة أشهر للقيام بالجانب العلمي،
two years to get it published. (Laughter)
وسنتين لنشره. (ضحك)
Typical science, actually, right? So this makes Amy and
أمر نمطي في العلم، في الواقع، أليس كذلك؟ وهذا يجعل إيمي
her friends the youngest published scientists in the world.
وأصدقائها أصغر العلماء الناشرين في العالم.
What was the feedback like?
كيف كانت ردود الأفعال؟
Well, it was published two days before Christmas,
حسنا، لقد تم نشرها يومين قبل الكريسماس،
downloaded 30,000 times in the first day, right?
تم تحميلها لـ 30,000 مرة في اليوم الأول، صحيح؟
It was the Editors' Choice in Science, which is a top science magazine.
كانت خيار المحررين في ساينس، وهي مجلة علمية مصنفة.
It's forever freely accessible by Biology Letters.
وهو متاح للوصول المجاني من طرف "رسائل علم الأحياء"
It's the only paper that will ever be freely accessible by this journal.
إنها الورقة العلمية الوحيدة التي ستكون متاحة مجانا من طرف هذه الدورية.
Last year, it was the second-most downloaded paper
في العام الماضي، كانت ثاني أكثر ورقة علمية تحميلا
by Biology Letters, and the feedback from not just scientists
في "رسائل علم الأحياء"، والتعليقات لم تكن فقط من طرف العلماء
and teachers but the public as well.
بل المعلمين والجمهور كذلك.
And I'll just read one.
سوف أقرأ فقط إحداها.
"I have read 'Blackawton Bees' recently. I don't have
"لقد قرأت "نحل بلاكاوتون" مؤخرا. ليست لدي
words to explain exactly how I am feeling right now.
عبارات أصف بها ما أشعر به الآن.
What you guys have done is real, true and amazing.
ما فعلتموه يا رفاق حقيقي وصحيح ومذهل.
Curiosity, interest, innocence and zeal are the most basic
الفضول والاهتمام والبراءة والحماس هي أساس
and most important things to do science.
ومن الأمور الأكثر أهمية للقيام بالعلم.
Who else can have these qualities more than children?
ومن غير الأطفال يتوفر على هذه الخصائص؟
Please congratulate your children's team from my side."
رجاء هنئ فريق أطفالك نيابة عني".
So I'd like to conclude with a physical metaphor.
أود أن أختم باستعارة مادية.
Can I do it on you? (Laughter)
هل يمكن أن أجربها عليكم؟ (ضحك)
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, come on. Yeah yeah. Okay.
أوه نعم، نعم، نعم، هيا. نعم نعم. حسنا.
Now, science is about taking risks, so this is an incredible risk, right? (Laughter)
الآن، العلم مرتبط بالمخاطرة، وبالتالي فهذه مخاطرة لا تصدق، صحيح؟ (ضحك)
For me, not for him. Right? Because we've only done this once before. (Laughter)
بالنسبة لي، ليس بالنسبة له. أليس كذلك؟ لأننا لقد فعلنا هذا مرة واحدة فقط من قبل. (ضحك)
And you like technology, right?
وأنت تحب التكنولوجيا، صحيح؟
Shimon Schocken: Right, but I like myself.
شيمون شوكن: نعم، ولكنني أحب نفسي.
BL: This is the epitome of technology. Right. Okay.
ب. ل: هذا مثال عن التكنولوجيا. صحيح. حسنا.
Now ... (Laughter)
الآن... (ضحك)
Okay. (Laughter)
حسنا. (ضحك)
Now, we're going to do a little demonstration, right?
الآن، سنقوم بعرض صغير، صحيح؟
You have to close your eyes, and you have to point
عليك أن تغمض عينيك، وعليك أن تشير
where you hear me clapping. All right?
حيث تسمعني أصفق. حسنًا؟
(Clapping)
(التصفيق)
Okay, how about if everyone over there shouts. One, two, three?
حسنا، ماذا لو صرخ جميع الجمهور هناك. واحد اثنان ثلاثة؟
Audience: (Shouts)
الجمهور: (صراخ)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Shouts) (Laughter)
(صراخ) (ضحك)
Brilliant. Now, open your eyes. We'll do it one more time.
ممتاز. الآن، افتح عينيك. وسوف تفعل ذلك مرة أخرى.
Everyone over there shout. (Shouts)
الجميع هناك اصرخوا. (يصرخ)
Where's the sound coming from? (Laughter) (Applause)
من أين يأتي الصوت؟ (ضحك) (تصفيق)
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا. (تصفيق)
What's the point? The point is what science does for us.
ما هي العبرة؟ العبرة هي ما يفعله العلم بنا.
Right? We normally walk through life responding,
أليس كذلك؟ نحن عادة نعيش حياتنا متجاوبين،
but if we ever want to do anything different, we have to
ولكن إن أردنا قط القيام بشيء مختلف، علينا
step into uncertainty. When he opened his eyes,
أن نخطو نحو الشك. عندما فتح عينيه،
he was able to see the world in a new way.
كان قادراً على رؤية العالم بطريقة جديدة.
That's what science offers us. It offers the possibility
وهذا ما يقدمه العلم لنا. إنه يوفر إمكانية
to step on uncertainty through the process of play, right?
الخطو نحو الشك عن طريق عملية اللعب، أليس كذلك؟
Now, true science education I think should be about
الآن، أعتقد أن التعليم الحقيقي للعلوم يجب أن يرتبط
giving people a voice and enabling to express that voice,
بإعطاء الناس صوتا وتمكينهم من التعبير عن ذلك الصوت،
so I've asked Amy to be the last voice in this short story.
ولهذا طلبت من إيمي أن تكون آخر صوت في هذه القصة القصيرة.
So, Amy?
حسنا، إيمي؟
AO: This project was really exciting for me,
إ. أ: كان هذا المشروع مثيرا حقاً بالنسبة لي،
because it brought the process of discovery to life,
نظراً لأنه جلب عملية الاكتشاف للحياة،
and it showed me that anyone, and I mean anyone,
وتبين لي أن أي شخص، وأعني أي شخص،
has the potential to discover something new,
لديه القدرة على اكتشاف شيء جديد،
and that a small question can lead into a big discovery.
وأن سؤالا صغيرا يمكن أن يؤدي إلى اكتشاف كبير.
Changing the way a person thinks about something
تغيير الطريقة التي يفكر بها شخص في شيء ما
can be easy or hard. It all depends on the way the person
يمكن أن يكون سهلا أو صعبا. كل شيء يتوقف على الطريقة التي يحس بها
feels about change.
الشخص حيال التغيير.
But changing the way I thought about science was
ولكن تغيير الطريقة التي فكرت بها في العلوم كان
surprisingly easy. Once we played the games
سهلا بشكل مدهش. بمجرد أن لعبنا الألعاب
and then started to think about the puzzle,
ثم بدأت في التفكير في هذا اللغز،
I then realized that science isn't just a boring subject,
أدركت آنذاك أن العلم ليس فقط موضوعا مملا،
and that anyone can discover something new.
وأن أي شخص يمكن أن يكتشف شيئا جديداً.
You just need an opportunity. My opportunity came
كنت فقط بحاجة إلى فرصة. جاءت لي الفرصة
in the form of Beau, and the Blackawton Bee Project.
في شكل بو، ومشروع نحل بلاكاوتون.
Thank you.BL: Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. ب. ل: شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)